<Document>
# Atmospherics

Atmospherics setups are a necessity for your long-term comfort but are generally undocumented, resulting in them being a bit tricky to set up. The following attempts to cover the basics.

## Standard Mix
Breathing pure O2 or pure N2 is generally bad for the health of your crew, and it is recommended to instead aim for a mix of [color=#a4885c]78% N2 and 22% O2 at 101.24kPa.[/color] It's recommended that your gas mixer setup be set to output at least 1000kPa for faster re-pressurization of rooms.
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OxygenCanister"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="NitrogenCanister"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="AirCanister"/>
</Box>
Variations on this mix may be necessary for the long-term comfort of atypical crew, for example crew who require a plasma gas mix to survive. For atypical crew, it is recommended to try and give them their own personal space, isolated by either airlock or disposals section. Keep in mind both methods are leaky and you will need scrubbers on both sides of the lock to clean up any leaked gasses.
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="PlasmaCanister"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="StorageCanister"/>
</Box>
## Vents and Scrubbers
Vents and scrubbers are core atmospherics devices that fill and cleanse rooms, respectively. By default, they are configured for filling rooms to standard pressure (101.24kPa) and to remove all non-O2/N2 gasses from a room. They can be reconfigured from their default settings, allowing you to configure how they respond to various types of gasses or pressure levels. This can be done by interacting with an existing air alarm nearby, or installing and connecting them to a new one.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="GasVentPump"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="GasVentScrubber"/>
</Box>
During standard operation, if a vent detects that the outside environment is space, it will automatically cease operation until a minimum pressure is reached to avoid destruction of necessary gasses. This can be fixed by pressurizing the room up to that minimum pressure by refilling it with gas canister (potentially multiple, if the room is of significant size).

Should you encounter a situation where scrubbers aren't cleaning a room fast enough, employ portable scrubbers by dragging them to the affected location and wrenching them down. They work much faster than typical scrubbers and can clean up a room quite quickly. Large spills may require you to employ multiple.
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="PortableScrubber"/>
</Box>
# Смешивание газов и камеры сгорания
В случае, если вы выполнили все поставленные задачи, вы можете получить дополнительную энергию или деньги, создавая новые химические газы.

## Тритий
Тритий - это прозрачный зелёный газ, который легко воспламеняется, радиоактивен и сгорает при контакте с кислородом, что делает его очень полезным при работе с [color=#a4885c]ТЭГ-ом[/color].
Его можно получить, сжигая 1% плазмы и 96% или более кислорода в камере сгорания. Вы можете извлечь этот газ с помощью скрубберов.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="PlasmaCanister" />
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OxygenCanister" />
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="GasVentScrubber"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="TritiumCanister" />
</Box>

## Фрезон
Фрезон - это голубовато-зелёный газ, очень сложный и очень опасный. Для получения фрезона необходимо смешать тритий, кислород и азот в помещении с температурой -203.15°C, чтобы запустить реакцию, а также предотвратить сгорание трития с кислородом.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="TritiumCanister" />
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="AirCanister" />
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="GasVentScrubber"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="StorageCanister" Caption="Канистра Фрезона"/>
</Box>

Важно понимать, что утечка фрезона может погубить станцию, превратив её в зимний ад с зудящими свитерами и обморожениями. Фрезон очень холодный и может заморозить станцию до смерти, если хотя бы несколько молей выберутся наружу, так что убедитесь, что вы заперли свои канистры или просто переместили фрезон прямо в хранилище.

## Справочный лист
- Стандартная атмосферная смесь - это [color=#a4885c]78% N2 и 22% O2 при давлении 101,24 кПа.[/color]
- Газ подчиняется реальной математике. Вы можете использовать уравнение PV = nRT (P - давление кПа * V - объем л = моли * R * температура К), чтобы получить информацию, которую вам нужно знать о газе. R - константа, приблизительно равна 8,31446.

</Document>
